Simon Fraser University Gallery fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Simon Fraser University Gallery fonds
1965 - 2001, predominant 1965 - 1987
F-90
3.32 m of textual records and other material
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION Fonds includes sound recordings (2 recordings on 4 audio cassettes, originals and copies) and photographic material (236 photographs, 136 slides, 94 negatives, and 24 contact sheets). GENERAL NOTE Sound recordings are located in series 1. Photographs are located in series 5-2 relating to exhibitions; see Appendix B for a list of files containing photographic material.
Simon Fraser University Gallery
The Simon Fraser Gallery was established as a public art gallery in 1970 by SFU President Kenneth Strand upon the recommendation of the President's Works of Art Committee. At the same time, he appointed James Warren Felter as University Art Curator. He was charged with directing the Gallery's program and serving as curator of the University's art collection known as the Simon Fraser Collection. The Gallery was administratively located in the Centre for Communications and the Arts. The Gallery and the Simon Fraser Collection provided the visual arts component of the Centre. In 1974, the collection had more than five hundred works of art, primarily of Canadian artists.
When the Centre for Communications and the Arts became the Centre for the Arts within the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies, the position of Curator/Director of Exhibitions became the Director of the Simon Fraser Gallery.
During the first ten years of its operation, the Gallery presented 127 exhibitions in its campus facility. In addition to organizing exhibitions and hosting circulating programs on the SFU campus, the Gallery developed its own program of circulating exhibitions to other public art galleries, principally in western Canada.
The 1983 programs of the Gallery reflected the University's growing financial crisis and the once extensive program of circulating exhibits was cut back. The new University President, William Saywell, restructured the Works of Art Committee. In 1984, Felter, who had been the chair of the committee, became its secretary and Professor Ed Gibson became chair. In June 1985, after receiving a proposed statement of policy from the President's Works of Arts Committee, President Saywell separated the Gallery from the Centre for the Arts to become an independent unit reporting to the Vice-President, Development. The new policy stated that the primary purpose of the Gallery was to enhance the aesthetic sensibilities of the entire University community as well as the general public. The University Art Curator, who acted as Director of the Gallery, would be responsible for planning and day to day Gallery operation.
In January 1986, Ed Gibson succeeded Jim Felter as Director of the Gallery. The President's Works of Art Committee expanded to become the Simon Fraser Gallery Board, with representation from faculty, students, staff and the community. It functioned in an advisory capacity to the Vice-President, Development.
published
Full
Revised
The title of the fonds is based on the name of its creator.
The fonds consists of records made or received by the Art Gallery in the process of carrying out is functions. Activities and events documented include the evolution of the Gallery's structure, functions and governance; management of the Gallery's budget; deliberations of advisory committees; correspondence of the director with other university departments and the community; and the production of numerous art exhibitions. Records include correspondence, reports, agendas, minutes, budget summaries, exhibition programs and flyers, lists and forms relating to exhibitions, news clippings, and other documents.
The records were arranged by the archivist.
Merler, Grazia; Richmond, Stuart; Richardson, Letia; Gibson, Edward; Felter, James W.; Sound recordings; Textual records; Arts and culture
The records were acquired by the Archives in several accessions through the application of University Records Retention Schedules and Disposal Authorities (RRSDAs).
All accessions have been processed as of February 2006. Further accruals are expected.
For other material related to the Art Gallery, see the fonds for the School for Contemporary Arts, "Departmental correspondence -- Art Gallery" (F-109-5-2) and "Simon Fraser Gallery Board Files" (F-109-4-32).
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File and item lists are available.
- History and organization files, 1965 - 1988; F-90-1; 26 cm of textual records 2 sound recordings; Physical description: includes 2 sound recordings on 4 audio cassettes (originals and copies).
  published
  Series consists of 13 files created by Nikki Sones relating to the evolution of the gallery and its programs. Records include correspondence, agendas, minutes, reports, budget summaries, news clippings, interview transcripts and audio cassettes.
  The historical project files were left as arranged by Nikki Sones. The archivist added the last two files in the series because they related to the history and organization of the Gallery.
  Nikki Sones also compiled several files on acquisitions and donors. These files were returned to the Art Gallery.
  All files in this series have been reviewed for access. With the exception of file 8, all are open. File 8 is "restricted in part"; it contains a 2 documents that have been "enclosed" (restricted and physically separated from the file) as they contain personal information of identifiable individuals (CVs); the remainder of the file is open. The sound recordings (in file 6) are audiocassettes, and access to the originals is restricted due to the fragility of the medium. The recordings been digitized, consult the reference archivist to access the digital copies.
  - Chronological summary and documentation, 1969 - 1974; F-90-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 90-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - Chronological summary and documentation, 1975 - 1982; F-90-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 90-1)
  - Chronological summary and documentation, 1983 - 1984; F-90-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 90-1)
  - Chronological summary and documentation, 1985; F-90-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 90-1)
  - Chronological summary and documentation, 1986 - 1988; F-90-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 90-1)
  - Interviews: transcripts, notes -- Felter, Strate, Voigt, Wasserman, 1988; F-90-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 90-1)
    N. Gerbrandt; Felter, James W.; Strate, Grant; Wassermann, Selma; Voight, Eva; Textual records
    - Interview: J.W. Felter, 2 June 1988; F-90-1-0-0-6-1 (Audio cassette OBJ-3272, Audio cassette OBJ-3273)
      Item is an interview of J.W. Felter by N. Gelbrandt, Research Assistant, on the history of the Gallery and its collection.
      Felter, James W.; N. Gerbrandt; Sound recordings
      Pending review
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-90-item1, F-90-item2.
    - Interview: G. Strate, 8 June 1988; F-90-1-0-0-6-2 (Audio cassette OBJ-3274, Audio cassette OBJ-3275)
      Item is an interview of Grant Strate by N. Gelbrandt, Research Assistant, on the history of the Gallery and its collection.
      N. Gerbrandt; Strate, Grant; Sound recordings
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-90-item3, F-90-item4.
  - Annual reports, 1974 - 1983; F-90-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 90-1)
  - Proposal for needs study by Brenda Berck, 1983; F-90-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 90-1)
    Berck, Brenda; Textual records
    Restricted in part
  - Maynard's report, 1986; F-90-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 90-1)
    Maynard's Appraisal Company; Textual records
  - The permanent collection, 1986; F-90-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 90-1)
  - Simon Fraser collection - works of art committee, 1965 - 1970; F-90-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 90-2)
    President's Works of Art Committee; Textual records
  - Simon Fraser collection - works of art committee, 1972 - 1985; F-90-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 90-2)
  - Budget, 1965 - 1986; F-90-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 90-2)
  - News clippings, 1972 - 1985; F-90-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 90-2)
  - Organization, 1976 - 1985; F-90-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 90-2)
- Committee files, 1971 - 1986; F-90-2; 9 cm of textual records
  Series consists primarily of records relating to the meetings and deliberations of the President's Works of Art Committee and its successor, the Simon Fraser Gallery Board. Records include agendas, minutes, supporting papers, and correspondence.
  See the fonds of the School for Contemporary Arts: "Simon Fraser Gallery Board Files" (F-109-4-32).
  Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release and, as a result of the review, access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  - President's Works of Art committee -- Norris proposal, 1971 - 1972; F-90-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - President's Works of Art committee - policy statements, 1974 - 1980; F-90-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - President's Works of Art committee - budgets / grants, 1979; F-90-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - President's Works of Art committee - correspondence, 1979; F-90-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - President's Works of Art committee - budgets / grants, 1980; F-90-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - President's Works of Art committee - memoranda, 1980; F-90-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - President's Works of Art committee - memoranda / correspondence, 1982; F-90-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - President's Works of Art committee - memoranda / correspondence, 1983; F-90-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - President's Works of Art committee - minutes, memoranda, 1984; F-90-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - President's Works of Art committee - agendas, minutes and papers, 1984 - 1985; F-90-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - President's Works of Art committee - minutes and papers, 1984 - 1985; F-90-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - President's Works of Art committee - policy development, 1984 - 1985; F-90-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - President's Works of Art committee - memoranda / correspondence, 1984 - 1985; F-90-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - Simon Fraser gallery board - minutes and papers, 1985 - 1986; F-90-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - Centre for the Arts - Gallery committee, 1982 - 1983; F-90-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
- Reports, 1968 - 1983; F-90-3; 4 cm of textual records
  Series consists primarily of the Art Gallery's annual reports from 1974 through 1983 written by James Warren Felter to describe the activities of the Gallery for those time periods. Series also contains two earlier reports—one describing the activities of the entire Centre for Communications and the Arts and the other, an early proposal by Felter regarding the future direction of the Gallery.
  - Centre for Communications and the Arts -- annual events report, 1968 - 1969; F-90-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
    School for the Contemporary Arts; Textual records
  - Report on exhibitions with a proposal for the future, 1969; F-90-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - Annual report, 1974; F-90-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - Annual report, 1975 - 1977; F-90-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - Annual report, 1981; F-90-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - Annual report, 1982; F-90-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
  - Annual report, 1983; F-90-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 90-3)
- Correspondence, 1969 - 1985; F-90-4; 51 cm of textual records; The first correspondence file, "Director's Corespondence 1967-1977) was collected by former Archives staff from other University sources.
  Series consists of correspondence relating to the duties of the Art Gallery director. Activities, events and topics documented include the planning and production of art exhibitions at SFU, the production of circulating exhibitions, the acquisition of art work for the Simon Fraser Collection, the provision of gallery space, applying for grants, and liaising with other University deparments and the community.
  - Correspondence - Director's, 1969 - 1977; F-90-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence - general, 1969; F-90-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence - memoranda, 1969; F-90-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence - general, 1970; F-90-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence - memoranda, 1970; F-90-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence - general, 1971; F-90-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence - memoranda, 1971; F-90-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence - general, 1972; F-90-4-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence - memoranda, 1972; F-90-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence - J.W. Felter, 1972; F-90-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence - general, 1973; F-90-4-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence - memoranda, 1973; F-90-4-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence - J.W. Felter, 1973; F-90-4-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence, 1974; F-90-4-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence - general, 1974; F-90-4-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 90-4)
  - Correspondence - memoranda, 1974; F-90-4-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 90-5)
  - Correspondence - J.W. Felter, 1974; F-90-4-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 90-5)
  - Correspondence, 1975; F-90-4-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 90-5)
  - Correspondence - general, 1975; F-90-4-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 90-5)
  - Correspondence - memoranda, 1975; F-90-4-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 90-5)
  - Correspondence, 1976; F-90-4-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 90-5)
  - Correspondence - memoranda, 1976; F-90-4-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 90-5)
  - Correspondence - J.W. Felter, 1976; F-90-4-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 90-5)
  - Correspondence, 1977; F-90-4-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 90-5)
  - Correspondence - memoranda, 1977; F-90-4-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 90-5)
  - Correspondence, 1978; F-90-4-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 90-6)
  - Gallery correspondence, 1979; F-90-4-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 90-6)
  - Gallery memoranda, 1979; F-90-4-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 90-6)
  - Gallery correspondence, vol. 1, 1980; F-90-4-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 90-6)
  - Gallery correspondence, vol. 2, 1980; F-90-4-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 90-6)
  - Gallery memoranda, 1980; F-90-4-0-0-31 (Archival box - standard 90-6)
  - Correspondence - J.W. Felter, 1980; F-90-4-0-0-32 (Archival box - standard 90-6)
  - Gallery correspondence, 1981; F-90-4-0-0-33 (Archival box - standard 90-7)
  - Gallery memoranda, 1981; F-90-4-0-0-34 (Archival box - standard 90-7)
  - Gallery correspondence, 1982; F-90-4-0-0-35 (Archival box - standard 90-7)
  - Gallery memoranda, 1982; F-90-4-0-0-36 (Archival box - standard 90-7)
  - Gallery correspondence, 1983; F-90-4-0-0-37 (Archival box - standard 90-7)
  - Gallery memoranda, 1983; F-90-4-0-0-38 (Archival box - standard 90-7)
  - Gallery correspondence, 1984; F-90-4-0-0-39 (Archival box - standard 90-7)
  - Gallery memoranda, 1984; F-90-4-0-0-40 (Archival box - standard 90-7)
  - Gallery correspondence, 1985; F-90-4-0-0-41 (Archival box - standard 90-7)
  - Gallery memoranda, 1985; F-90-4-0-0-42 (Archival box - standard 90-7)
- Exhibition files, 1968-2001, predominant 1968-1987; F-90-5; 2.43 m of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the production of in-house and travelling exhibitions. Records include correspondence, flyers, programs, statistics and other documents.
  - Exhibition files -- general, 1968 - 1983; F-90-5-1; 12 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records relating to the general production of exhibitions. Activities, events and topics documented include attendance statistics, visitors' comments, and exhibition planning. Records include statistics, comment sheets, flyers, invitations, schedules, newsclippings, budget summaries, correspondence, and other documents.
    - Exhibitions - general, 1968 - 1983; F-90-5-1-0-1 (Archival box - small 90-8)
    - Attendance statistics and visitor comments, 1971; F-90-5-1-0-2 (Archival box - small 90-8)
    - Attendance statistics, 1971 - 1980; F-90-5-1-0-3 (Archival box - small 90-8)
    - Attendance statistics and visitor comments, 1973; F-90-5-1-0-4 (Archival box - small 90-8)
    - Exhibition budget, 1973; F-90-5-1-0-5 (Archival box - small 90-8)
    - Exhibition budget, 1981; F-90-5-1-0-6 (Archival box - small 90-8)
    - Exhibition planning, 1970; F-90-5-1-0-7 (Archival box - small 90-8)
    - Exhibition planning, 1971; F-90-5-1-0-8 (Archival box - small 90-8)
    - Exhibition planning, 1972; F-90-5-1-0-9 (Archival box - small 90-8)
    - Exhibition planning, 1973; F-90-5-1-0-10 (Archival box - small 90-8)
    - Exhibition planning, 1974; F-90-5-1-0-11 (Archival box - small 90-8)
  - Individual exhibition files, 1968-2001, predominant 1968-1987; F-90-5-2; 2.37 m of textual records and other material; Dates: the exhibition case files (one file for each exhibition) run to 1987; after this year, there are only 2 additional files (266 and 267) containing material relating to exhibitions generally. Physical description: includes 236 photographic prints, 136 slides, 94 negatives, and 24 contact sheets. General note: access points have been assigned at the file level for the names of the artists in cases where an exhibition represents the work or one or several artists; but no attempt has been made to register name access points for collective exhibitions involving a large number of individual artists. General note: many files contain photographs relating to the exhibition; see list in Appendix B.
    Sub-series consists of records relating to the production of individual art exhibitions. Records include programs, flyers, correspondence, budget statements, visitors' comments, lists of art works, price lists, notes, working papers, and posters.
    - Exhibition programs, 1968 - 1969; F-90-5-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
    - Art events, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
    - Earth to moon, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      National Aeronautics and Space Agency; Textual records
    - Clippings - art exhibitions events, 1969 - 1982; F-90-5-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
    - Lynne Harrison, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Harrison, Lynne; Textual records
    - King watercolours, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition ran from June 16 - July 4, 1969.
      Wayne King; Textual records
    - Pleasantries and not so, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Feb. 18-21, 1969.
      Fritz Hunrath; Textual records
    - Toni Onley 13 drawings, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place in Jan. 1969.
      Toni Onley; Textual records
    - Burnaby young art, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      YMCA (Burnaby); Textual records
    - Glenn Alps prints, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Jan. 13-31, 1969.
      Glen Alps; Textual records
    - Group of non, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Feb. 17 - Mar. 14, 1969.
      Group of NON; Textual records
    - One month, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-12 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Mar. 17 - 28, 1969.
      Siegelaub, Seth; Textual records
    - Canadian graphics, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-13 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Apr. 9 - 23, 1969.
    - Untitled exhibition, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-14 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between May 19 - June 19, 1969.
      N.E. Thing Co. Ltd; Robert Barry; Joseph Kosuth; Sol LeWitt; Lawrence Weiner; Douglas Huebler; Jan Dibbets; Terry Atkinson; Baxter, Iain; Michael Baldwin; Stephen Kaltenbach; Textual records; Photographic materials
    - Smallest exhibit, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-15 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between June 2-6, 1969.
      Smith, Joel; Textual records
    - Ecuador exhibits, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-16 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between June 9 - July 4, 1969.
      Villacis, Anibal; Katja Kohn; Leon Davalos; Oswaldo Guayasamin; Rodrigues, Carlos; Mario Porras; Galo Galecio; Galo Galecio; Eduardo Peroglio; Patrico Gudino; Textual records
    - San Francisco exhibit: 18'6" x 6'9" x 11'2.5" ..., 1969; F-90-5-2-0-17 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between July 7 - Aug. 1, 1969.
      Michael Asher; Robert Barry; Baxter, Iain; James Lee Byars; Eugenia Butler; Douglas Huebler; Stephen Kaltenbach; Kienholz, Edward; Joseph Kosuth; Le Va, Barry; Dennis Oppenheim; Eric Orr; Jim Rudnick; Robert Watts; Lawrence Weiner; Textual records
    - Herzog photography, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-18 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Oct. 7 - 18, 1969.
      Fred Herzog; Textual records
    - Sudeten German art, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-19 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Oct. 21 - 28, 1969.
    - Book of Job, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-20 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Nov. 24 - Dec. 13, 1969.
      William Blake; Textual records
    - Cuba today, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-21 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between June 23 - July 18, 1969.
    - Shirley Smith photos, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-22 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Oct. 7-28, 1969.
      Shirley A. Smith; Textual records
    - Gregg Simpson, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-23 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Nov. 4-21, 1969.
      Gregg Simpson; Textual records
    - The Inca collection, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-24 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Rymsza, Andrew de Lilio; Textual records
    - Squibb photographs, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-25 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Nov. 24 - Dec. 12, 1969.
      Squibb, Bill; Textual records
    - Bella Coola exhibits, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-26 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Westman, Tony; Hobler, Philip M.; Textual records
    - Black art, 1969; F-90-5-2-0-27 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Oct. 7-18, 1969.
      Jones, Abi; Textual records
    - Exhibition program, 1970; F-90-5-2-0-28 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Summer 1970.
    - Exhibition program, 1970; F-90-5-2-0-29 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Winter 1970.
    - J.K. Esler graphics, 1970; F-90-5-2-0-30 (Archival box - standard 90-9)
      Exhibition took place between Fall - Sept. 2-18, 1970.
      J.K. Esler; Textual records